Alfred Terhune Collection Relating to Edward FitzGerald
Alfred Terhune Collection relating to Edward FitzGerald
1841-1978
Terhune, Alfred McKinley, 1899-1975
14 linear ft., 76 reels of microfilm.
Papers of the American professor, biographer. Correspondence, writings, notes, and FitzGerald memorabilia brought together by Terhune to support his ongoing research which culminated in the publication of the four-volume The Letters of Edward FitzGerald (1830-1883), an effort begun by Terhune and completed after his death by his wife Annabelle Burdick Terhune. In addition to FitzGerald, the collection is representative of the interests of a number of individuals (Henry B. Lister, Waldo Maas, Terhune) and organizations (most notably the Omar Khayyam Club), and spans nearly a century of collecting tastes and history. It is therefore also a resource for other notable 19th century British writers and scholars including Bernard Barton, Francis Capper Brooke, E.B. Cowell, George Crabbe, Joseph Fletcher, A.P. Moor, Bernard Quaritch, Alfred Tennyson, and William Makepeace Thackeray. It also provides much information about Suffolk, England and its environs as well as insights into the character of the Victorian period.
149404
Biographical History
Edward FitzGerald (1809-1883), born Edward Marlborough Purcell, was a British poet, best known as the author of the first and most famous English translation of The Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam.
Alfred Terhune (1899-1975) was a professor of English at Syracuse University; his life-long interest in FitzGerald resulted in a comprehensive four-volume edition of The Letters of Edward FitzGerald (1830-1883).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alfred M. Terhune Collection Relating to Edward FitzGerald consists of a variety of materials -- correspondence, memorabilia, notes, printed material, writings, and miscellaneous items -- both by and about Edward FitzGerald. The collection was assembled by Syracuse University English Professor Alfred Terhune in support of his research on FitzGerald, which eventually resulted in the publication of The Letters of Edward FitzGerald (1830-1883) (4 volumes). Although the collection is focused on FitzGerald and appears highly integrated, it should nevertheless be viewed as a combination of disparate items, representative of the interests of a number of individuals (Henry Bertram Lister, Waldo Maas, Terhune) and organizations (most notably the Omar Khayyam Club), and spanning nearly a century of collecting tastes and history. As such, the collection consists of a wide variety of materials concerning Edward FitzGerald and his associates, running the gamut from the funereal (FitzGerald obituaries and will) to the lighthearted (Omar Khayyam Club menus and seating charts); the scholarly (original FitzGerald correspondence, a Thackeray bookplate) to the mythic (a rose from the tomb of Omar Khayyam).
Despite his quiet lifestyle, FitzGerald was as personable in his private life as he was multi-faceted in his literary career. It is indicative of the complexity of his character that he inspired so diverse a range of admirers (E.B. Cowell, George Crabbe, Joseph Fletcher, Fanny Kemble, A.P. Moor, Alfred Tennyson, William Makepeace Thackeray, W. Aldis Wright). The Terhune collection illuminates the many sides of FitzGerald's personality and provides insight into those individuals (Maas, Terhune, Lister) who studied, recorded, and, above all, shared a fascination with his life. The collection has been organized to reflect the range of both primary and secondary FitzGerald material, and includes original FitzGerald letters; incoming and outgoing correspondence of his associates, many containing references to FitzGerald; a section of FitzGerald miscellany, consisting primarily of memorabilia and printed material; the Waldo Maas files; and Terhune's correspondence and research notes, including 76 reels of microfilm containing FitzGerald letters.
The first section of the collection, Edward FitzGerald Letters, consists of 45 outgoing items of FitzGerald correspondence written between 1844 and 1883, a small fragment of his voluminous output of letters, yet illuminating the man and his interests. Evidence of FitzGerald's playful Spirit is a letter to Anna Biddle, thanking her for her gift of apples (4 Nov. 1873):
What you sent me were really beautiful little Fellows; cherubic looking Apple-lets; it seemed a pity to eat them; and I don't think they were Quite so good as handsome.
Characteristic of the many FitzGerald letters which discuss literature is this observation to Anna Biddle (29 Dec. 1876):
I will only say of "Harold" that I think AT [Alfred Tennyson] had better been of my mind in not writing, or publishing, more. These latter Inferiorities will temporarily, though not justly, cloud his present Reputation and be a Drag upon those works of his which are to live. So I think.
The next section of the Terhune collection is the Edward FitzGerald Associates' Letters which are chronologically arranged and span 1846 through 1943, many of which contain references to the translator and his work. A letter from a Quaker poet Bernard Barton to George Crabbe, son of the poet, recounts an anecdote FitzGerald enjoyed telling (6 Aug. 1846): "I longed to follow the example of Edward Fgd's friend Squire Jenney who heroically doffs the trowsers, & sits with only calico drawers an--so I am told." However, not all the letters in the Associates' section are light in tone. Following FitzGerald's death in 1883, many of the correspondents discuss the funeral arrangements and the practical aspects of the author's work, such as the copyright of his translation of the Rubaiyat.
The next division of the Terhune collection is designated FitzGerald Miscellany. The items in this section are related to FitzGerald both in terms of subject and time period, and comprise engravings, Omar Khayyam Club menus and seating charts, manuscripts by Henry B. Lister, photographs, postcards, printed material, and other items of memorabilia. This section includes a rare manuscript poem by FitzGerald, "A Country Carol."
The Waldo Maas files follow the FitzGerald Miscellany and consist primarily of Maas' correspondence and notebooks. An early FitzGerald collector, Maas accumulated a large assortment of material in anticipation of publishing FitzGerald's letters. Although the exact sequence and timing are unclear, it appears that the Maas collection was acquired for Terhune's work, and that some Maas items became integrated with his own research material. In the arrangement of the Terhune collection, the original Maas folders and item numbers, when available, have been retained. (A number of items of memorabilia which Maas collected may be found in the FitzGerald Miscellany.) Assembled primarily during the first half of the 20th century, the Maas files are reflective of early research work an FitzGerald. The Maas correspondence is particularly significant for its exchange of information with people who had known FitzGerald as well as a number of FitzGerald scholars. Maas' three-year correspondence with Amy I. Biddell is noteworthy for its extent as well as its illuminating discussions of FitzGerald and the Biddell family. The humor and sympathy of these letters demonstrates FitzGerald's capacity to touch many lives nearly a century after his death. Also included in this section is a series of notebooks containing the typed transcripts of FitzGerald letters which Maas was able to obtain from a variety of sources.
The fifth division of the collection are the Terhune Correspondence-Subject Files which consists primarily of incoming letters about FitzGerald. In addition to the correspondence related to bibliographical questions and the ordering of books, there are also a number of letters which include discussions of various aspects of FitzGerald's life and work. The most voluminous and perhaps most interesting of Terhune's exchanges is with author Frank Hussey who wrote a monograph on FitzGerald and sailing. While the letters focus on FitzGerald's love of the sport, they also provide source material on Suffolk and its environs during the Victorian era.
The Terhune Writings follow the Correspondence-Subject File and consist of the typescript manuscript of Terhune's dissertation, "Edward FitzGerald: a Biography," and the typescript of The Letters of Edward FitzGerald. This four- volume set was edited by Terhune and his wife, Annabelle, who completed the project following her husband's death.
The last section of the collection is the Terhune Research Notes, an assemblage of biographical material and background information which Terhune accumulated during his years of research on FitzGerald. Material relates to FitzGerald's associates as well as the various periods of the author's life. Extensive documentation for many of the FitzGerald letters describes how undated letters were chronologically ordered and elucidates for the modern reader some of the more obscure passages contained in the letters. This section has many useful bibliographical references and provides insight into not only the various aspects of FitzGerald's life but also Terhune's research methodology.
The Terhune collection is thus an excellent resource for information, both primary and secondary, on Edward FitzGerald.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arrangement varies; see Scope and Contents above.
Related Material
The manuscript collection is supported by an assortment of nearly 300 editions of the Rubaiyat, including copies of FitzGerald's first edition English translation of the Persian classic by Omar Khayyam. These reside in the Rare Books collection; please see for a complete listing.
The Terhune Collection is also supplemented by two additional manuscript sources: the
George Crabbe Collection
which relates to FitzGerald's death and the disposition of his estate, and the
Robert Bernard Martin
manuscript of With Friends Possessed: a Life of Edward FitzGerald, a biographical study published in 1985.
Subject and Genre Headings
Biography; Literature -- British; Barton, Bernard, 1784-1849.; Brooke, Francis Capper.; Cowell, Edward B. (Edward Byles), 1826-1903.; Crabbe, George.; FitzGerald, Edward, 1809-1883.; Fletcher, Joseph.; Hussey, Frank, 1906-; Kerrich, Mary Eleanor FitzGerald.; Lister, Henry Bertram, 1869-; Maas, Waldo.; Moor, A. P.; Omar Khayyam.; Quaritch, Bernard, 1819-1899.; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892.; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863.; Terhune, Alfred McKinley, 1899-1975.; Terhune, Annabelle Burdick.; Omar Khayyam Club (London, England); Omar Khayyam Club of America.; The Letters of Edward FitzGerald.; Rubaiyat.; Authors, English -- 19th century.; Biographers -- United States.; Great Britain -- Social life and customs.; Suffolk (England) -- Social life and customs.; Articles.; Bookplates.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Maps (documents); Memorabilia.; Notebooks.; Notes (documents); Obituaries.; Photographs.; Wills.; Biographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alfred M. Terhune.
Inventory
- Edward FitzGerald letters
  - John Barton, 1844 Sept. 17 (Box 1)
  - Mrs. Edward Donne, 1854 Mar. 7 (Box 1)
  - Anna Crabbe, 1863 Jan. 23 (Box 1)
  - George Moor, 1866 May 22 (Box 1)
  - Frederick Spalding, 1866 June 29 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Woolner, 1867 Mar. 8 (Box 1)
  - "Dear Sir", 1867 Sept. 8 (Box 1)
  - James Spedding, 1868 May 17 (Box 1)
  - drawing of boat, 1869 Aug. (Box 1)
  - Joseph Fletcher, 1870 Feb. 11 (Box 1)
  - Joseph Fletcher, 1870 Mar. 15 (Box 1)
  - Frederick Spalding, 1870 Sept. 7 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Elliott (Browne), 1871 Dec. 30 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1872 Mar. 5 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1872 Apr. 8 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1872 June 26 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Watts, 1872 Aug. 4 (Box 1)
  - Edward Byles Cowell, 1873 Jan. 4 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1873 Jan. 28 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1873 Nov. 4 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1874 Aug. 20 (Box 1)
  - Blanche Donne, 1875 Feb. 23 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1876 Jan. 23 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1876 Sept. 15 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1876 Sept. 19 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1876 Dec. 29 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1877 Jan. 22 (Box 1)
  - A.P. Moor, 1877 Mar. 7 (Box 1)
  - Valentia Donne, 1877 Mar. 20 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1878 Feb. 28 (Box 1)
  - Blanche Donne, 1878 Oct. 24 (Box 1)
  - Bernard Quaritch (incoming transcript), 1879 Jan. 17 (Box 1)
  - Blanche Donne, 1879 May 14 (Box 1)
  - Blanche Donne, 1879 Aug. 8 (Box 1)
  - Charles Keene, 1880 Feb. 8 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1880 Mar. 13 (Box 1)
  - Charles Keene, 1880 Mar. 28 (Box 1)
  - Francis Capper Brooke, 1880 July 26 (Box 1)
  - Anna Biddell, 1881 May 14 (Box 1)
  - Blanche Donne, 1881 Dec. (Box 1)
  - Blanche Donne, 1882 Jan. 24 (Box 1)
  - H.S. Wilson, 1882 Jan. 26 (Box 1)
  - Blanche Donne, 1882 Feb. 10 (Box 1)
  - Blanche Donne, 1882 Nov. 1 (Box 1)
  - Francis Capper Brooke, 1883 June 4 (Box 1)
  - Francis Capper Brooke, 1883 June 12 (Box 1)
- Edward FitzGerald associates' letters
  To locate specific correspondents, see Selected index to Edward FitzGerald Associates' Letters at the end of this finding aid.
  - Correspondence, 1841; 1846; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1852; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1865; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1877; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1880; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1883; 13 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1884; 6 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1887; 4 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1889; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1897; 5 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1899-1900; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1901; 4 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1902; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1904; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1905-1906; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1909-1910; 5 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1923; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1928; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1935; 1943; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Undated; 5 letters (Box 1)
- Edward FitzGerald miscellany
  - Admission card for Savile Club "With Mr. Edward Clodd's compliments L.W. Mosher" (Box 1)
  - "Analysis of Will of Edward FitzGerald Esquire", 1883 (Box 1)
  - Arnold, William Harris, extract from Ventures in Book Collecting (Box 1)
  - Auctioneers' particulars for sale of "Little Grange", Dec. 12, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Autograph (Edward FitzGerald) (Box 1)
  - Barton, Lucy, certificate of birth (copy) (Box 1)
  - Biddell, Herman, "John Loder of Woodbridge", manuscript (Box 1)
  - Biddell, Herman, sketch of horse (Box 1)
  - Book sale statement (Box 1)
  - Bookplate by Thackeray (Box 1)
  - Collection of FitzGerald oddments in volume with spine title Percival Stockdale & Baldock Black Horse (Box 1)
  - Edward FitzGerald Centenary (1809-1883) (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Dinner menu (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 1)
    - Sermon, M.B. Cowell (Box 1)
  - Edwards, Edwin, proofs of etching for Omar Khayyam (Box 1)
  - Edwards, Edwin, proofs of etching for Omar Khayyam, correspondence (Box 1)
  - Engraving of David Garrick, presentation by Edward FitzGerald to Herman Biddell (Box 2)
  - Engravings, various, relating to Suffolk and FitzGerald (Box 2)
  - FitzGerald/Thackeray correspondence, extract from The Connoisseur, Vol. XXXIX, May-Aug. 1914 (Box 2)
  - Illustrations, FitzGerald (Box 2)
  - Leaves of rose tree from Omar Khayyam's tomb and later planted on FitzGerald's grave at Boulge (Box 2)
  - Letter from Inland Revenue concerning unpaid taxes on Edward FitzGerald's income (Box 2)
  - Letters & papers relating to Edward FitzGerald (1883) (spine title Notices of Edward FitzGerald) (Box 2)
  - Lister, Henry Bertram
    - Correspondence, printed material (Box 2)
    - "Apochryphal Quatrains of the Rubaiyat" manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Omar Visits Hades" manuscript (Box 2)
    - "The Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam" manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam: Orphan Quatrains" manuscript (Box 2)
    - "'The Rubaiyat' Quatrains 1201 to 1268 and Omar's Stag Party" manuscript (Box 2)
    - "The Unorthodox Rubaiyat" manuscript (Box 2)
  - Memorandum books, Herman Biddell's wife, 2 books (Box 2)
  - Memorandum book, Mrs. M. Biddell (Box 2)
  - Notice of bequest to National Gallery of Latour portrait of Mr. and Mrs. Edwin Edwards (Box 2)
  - Omar Khayyam and music, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Omar Khayyam Club
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Dinner menu, 13 Oct. 1892 (Box 2)
    - Dinner menu, 20 June 1896 (Box 2)
    - Dinner menu, 20 Nov. 1896 (Box 2)
    - Dinner menu, clipping from The Sketch, 25 Mar. 1897 (Box 2)
    - "Ros Rosarum, " read at dinner, 10 July 1897 (Box 2)
    - Dinner menu, 27 Apr. 1898 (Box 2)
    - Clipping about dinner, 16 Dec. 1898 (Box 2)
    - Dinner menu, 5 Apr. 1900 (Box 3)
    - Dinner menu, 29 Nov. 1900 (Box 3)
    - Dinner menu, seating chart, 29 Nov. 1900 (Box 3)
    - Dinner menu, 13 Nov. 1908 (Box 3)
    - Dinner menu, 22 June 1909 (Box 3)
    - Dinner menu, 27 June 1936 (Box 3)
    - Dinner menu, 19 Nov. 1936 (Box 3)
    - Dinner menu, seating chart, 24 Nov. 1938 (Box 3)
    - Dinner menu, 16 Nov. 1949 (Box 3)
    - Dinner menu, seating chart, 16 Nov. 1949 (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Airy Family (Box 3)
    - Biddell Family (Box 3)
    - Clarkson, Thomas (Box 3)
    - Moor Family (Box 3)
    - Smith, Alfred (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, of Edward FitzGerald interest (Box 3)
  - Poetry
    - "Bredfield Hall" printed material (Box 3)
    - "A Country Carol" manuscript. poem (Box 3)
    - "A Country Carol" transcription (Box 3)
    - "A Country Carol" musical score by T. Tertius Noble (Box 3)
    - "A Country Carol" sales paraphernalia (Box 3)
  - Postcards with Edward FitzGerald interest, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Prendergast (Gen.) "Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam" manuscript. (Box 3)
  - Printed material, clippings (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
  - Printed material (by author)
    - Aubrey-Jones, George, See Elliott, R. W.
    - Clodd, Edward. "Edward FitzGerald," The English Illustrated Magazine, Feb. 1894 (Box 3)
    - Cooper, E. R. "Three FitzGerald letters," The Yachting World, Jan. 5, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Dole, Nathan Haskell. "Edward FitzGerald (1809-1883)" (Box 3)
    - Elliott, R. W. "King Edward VI School, Bury St. Edmunds"; Aubrey-Jones, George. "Suffolk Tales of a Suffolk Parson," East Anglian Magazine, Vol. IV, No. 5, Mar. 1939 (Box 3)
    - Ganz, Charles. "Edward FitzGerald" (leaflet) (Box 3)
    - Groome, Francis Hindes. Article on FitzGerald extracted from Chamber's Cyclopaedia of English Literature, Vol. III, 1903 (Box 3)
    - Hervey, Arthur. Playford and the Feltons (Box 3)
    - Kerrich, Mary Eleanor FitzGerald. "Edward FitzGerald: A Personal Reminiscence," The Nineteenth Century, no. 385, Mar. 1909 (Box 3)
    - Kerrich, Mary Eleanor FitzGerald. "Memories of Edward FitzGerald," East Anglian Magazine, Vol. 1, no. 2, Aug. 1935 (Box 3)
    - Kerrich, Mary Eleanor FitzGerald. "More Memories of FitzGerald," East Anglian Magazine, Vol. 1, no. 2, Nov. 1935 (Box 3)
    - Perry, Thomas Sergeant. "Mr. Edward FitzGerald's Translations," Atlantic, June 1877 (Box 3)
    - Potter, Ambrose G. "Omar Khayyam & His Rubaiyats," Ismaili Africa Birthday, No. 7, June 13, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Sykes, Major P. M. "A Pilgrimage to the Tomb of Omar Khayyam," Travel & Exploration, Sept. 1909 (Box 3)
    - Tennyson, C. "George Crabbe and Suffolk," The Geographical Magazine, July, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Whitten, Wilfred. "Edward FitzGerald," The Bookman, Vol. XXVIII, no. 165, June 1905 (Box 3)
    - Wright, William Aldis. "Edward FitzGerald," The Athenaeum, No. 3221, July 20, 1889 (Box 4)
  - Printed material (by publication title), A-Nd, 15 folders (Box 4)
  - Printed material (by publication title), Ne-W, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Sales paraphernalia, FitzGerald/Omar Khayyam (Box 5)
  - Thackeray, William Makepeace, See Bookplate by Thackeray.
  - Tracings of signature, John Loder and Edward FitzGerald (Box 5)
- Waldo Maas
  - "Brief particulars of a collection of books by and about Edward FitzGerald and his friends" (Box 5)
  - Correspondence-Subject File
    - Biddell, Amy I., 1942-1946; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Biddell, Amy I. articles (transcript) (Box 5)
    - Biddell, Herman article (transcript) (Box 5)
    - Board of Trade, 1943 (Box 5)
    - British Museum, 1944 (Box 5)
    - Clodd, Phyllis, 1943 (Box 5)
    - Colchester and Essex Museum, 1943 (Box 5)
    - Cooper, Ernest R., 1943 (Box 5)
    - Cowell, Mary, 1943 (Box 5)
    - The Daily Telegraph articles (transcripts) (Box 5)
    - De Polnay, Peter, 1946 (Box 5)
    - East Anglian Daily Times, 1942-1943 (Box 6)
    - Folger Shakespeare Library, 1943 (Box 6)
    - Ganz, Charles, 1938-1948 (Box 6)
    - Goodyear, A. C., 1943-1944 (Box 6)
    - Hannay, Neilson Campbell, 1942-1943 (Box 6)
    - Ipswich Public Library, 1942-1943 (Box 6)
    - Johnson, Catherine B. (nee C.B. Donne), 1943 (Box 6)
    - Kerrich, Mary Eleanor FitzGerald, 1943-1948 (Box 6)
    - Kerrich, Olivia, 1934-1943 (Box 6)
    - Lay, C. H., 1943-1944 (Box 6)
    - Ling, E. S. (Mrs.), 1943 (Box 6)
    - Ling, George S., 1943 (Box 6)
    - Maggs Bros., Report of Various Editions of Omar Khayyam (Box 6)
    - National Buildings Record, 1942-1943 (Box 6)
    - Pollock, John, 1942 (Box 6)
    - Redstone, Lilian J., 1942 (Box 6)
    - Smith, Fred, 1943 (Box 6)
    - Trevelyan, George Macaulay, See Trinity College (University of Cambridge)
    - Trinity College (University of Cambridge), 1943 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1943 (Box 6)
  - Notebooks
    - "Letters & Material Relating to Edward FitzGerald" (Box 6)
    - "Copies of Original Letters mainly from or about E.F.G." cover (Box 6)
    - "Copies of Original Letters mainly from or about E.F.G." (Box 6)
    - "Cuttings of & re E.F.G. (Edward FitzGerald)", 2 folders (Box 6)
    - "Copies of Magazine Articles on E.F.G. and Omar Kh'ayy'am" cover (Box 6)
    - "Copies of Magazine Articles on E.F.G. and Omar Kh'ayy'am", 2 folders (Box 6)
    - "Edward FitzGerald Letters (1830-1849) (1-240)" cover (Box 6)
    - "Edward FitzGerald Letters (1830-1849) (1-240)", 3 folders (Box 7)
    - "Edward FitzGerald Letters (1850-1869) (241-545)" cover (Box 7)
    - "Edward FitzGerald Letters (1850-1869) (241-545)", 3 folders (Box 7)
    - "Edward FitzGerald Letters (1870-1876) (546-824)" cover (Box 7)
    - "Edward FitzGerald Letters (1870-1876) (546-824)", 4 folders (Box 7)
    - "Edward FitzGerald Letters (1877-1883) (825-1118)" cover (Box 7)
    - "Edward FitzGerald Letters (1877-1883) (825-1118)", 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Writings
    - "Notes on the Posthumous Publication of Edward FitzGerald's Collected Works" (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 4)
- Terhune correspondence-subject files
  - A-Z (Box 8)
  - William H. Allen (bookseller), 1957-1964 (Box 8)
  - Arberry, Arthur John, 1961 (Box 8)
  - Armitage, Ethel, 1939 (Box 8)
  - Briscoe, Arnold Daly, 1938-1973 (Box 8)
  - Charlesworth, Eric C., 1964 (Box 8)
  - Charnwood, Dorothea Mary Roby (Thorpe), 1956 (Box 8)
  - Cook, Thomas E., 1953-1974; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Cooper, Winifred, 1970 (Box 8)
  - Crowfoot, Elisabeth, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
  - G. David (bookseller), 1961-1965 (Box 8)
  - De Soyres, John and Madeleine, 1947-1965 (Box 8)
  - Ehrsam, Theodore George, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Fall, Christine, 1956 (Box 8)
  - Galloway & Porter, Ltd., 1939-1961 (Box 8)
  - Ganz, Charles, 1942 (Box 8)
  - Gathorne-Hardy, Robert, 1938 (Box 8)
  - Groom, J. L., 1947 (Box 8)
  - W. Heffer & Sons, 1939-1970; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Henderson, John, 1929-1938 (Box 9)